<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> 
<!DOCTYPE Book SYSTEM "gapdoc.dtd">

<Book Name="HAPprog">

<TitlePage>

  <Title><Package>Hap Programming</Package> &ndash; An experimental framework
for objectifying the data structures of Hap</Title>

  <Version>( development version of
<#Include SYSTEM "today.ver">
 )
  </Version>
  <Author>Marc Röder
    <Email>marc.roeder(at)nuigalway.ie</Email>
  </Author>

  <Abstract>
   This extension does not change the behaviour of Hap and is fully
   backwards-compatible. It is not a part of Hap and there is no guarantee that
   it will at any point be supported by Hap. Use at your own risk.
  </Abstract>

  <Address>
  Marc Röder, Department of Mathematics, NUI Galway, Irleland
  </Address>

  <Acknowledgements>
  This work was supported by Marie Curie Grant No. MTKD-CT-2006-042685
  </Acknowledgements>

  <Copyright>&copyright; 2007 Marc Röder. <P/>

    This package is distributed under the terms of the GNU General
    Public License version 2 or later (at your convenience). See the  file
    <File>LICENSE</File> or 
    <URL>http://www.gnu.org/copyleft/gpl.html</URL>

  </Copyright>
</TitlePage>

<TableOfContents/>


<Body>
<Chapter Label="hapresolution"><Heading>Resolutions in Hap</Heading>

This document is only concerned with the representation of resolutions in
Hap. Note that it is not a part of Hap. The framework provided here is just an
extension of Hap data types used in HAPcryst and HAPprime. 
<P />
From now on, let <M>G</M> be a group and <M>\dots \to M_n\to M_{n-1}\to\dots\to M_1\to M_0\to Z</M> be a
resolution with free <M>ZG</M> modules <M>M_i</M>.

<P/>
The elements of the modules <M>M_i</M> can be represented in different
ways. This is what makes different representations for resolutions
desirable. First, we will look at the standard representation
(<C>HapResolutionRep</C>) as it is defined in Hap. After that, we will present
another representation for infinite groups.
Note that all non-standard representations must be sub-representations of the
standard representation to ensure compatibility with Hap.




<Section Label="hapresolutionrep"><Heading>The Standard Representation <K>HapResolutionRep</K></Heading>

For every <M>M_i</M> we fix a basis and number its elements. Furthermore, it is
assumed that we have a (partial) enumeration of the group of a resolution.
In practice this is done by generating a lookup table on the fly.
<P/>

In standard representation, the elements of the modules <M>M_k</M> are
represented by lists -"words"- of pairs of integers. A letter <C>[i,g]</C> of
such a word consists of the number of a basis element <C>i</C> or <C>-i</C> for
its additive inverse and a number
<M>g</M> representing a group element.
<P/>

A <C>HapResolution</C> in <C>HapResolutionRep</C> representation is a component
object with the components

<List>
<Item><C>group</C>, a group of arbitrary type.</Item>

<Item><C>elts</C>, a (partial) list of (possibly duplicate) elements in G. This
list provides the "enumeration" of the group. Note that there are
functions in Hap which assume that <C>elts[1]</C> is the identity element of G.
</Item>

<Item><C>appendToElts(g)</C>  a function that appends the group element
   <C>g</C> to <C>.elts</C>. This is not documented in Hap 1.8.6 but seems to
   be required for infinite groups. This requirement might vanish in some later
   version of Hap [G. Ellis, private communication].
</Item>

<Item><C>dimension(k)</C>, a function which returns the ZG-rank of the Module
<M>M_k</M></Item>

<Item><C>boundary(k,j)</C>, a function which returns the image in <M>M_{k-1}</M>
of the <M>j</M>th free generator of <M>M_k</M>. Note that negative <M>j</M> are
valid as input as well. In this case the additive inverse of the boundary of
the <M>j</M>th generator is returned</Item>

<Item><C>homotopy(k,[i,g])</C> a function which returns the image in
<M>M_{k+1}</M>, under a contracting homotopy <M>M_k \to M_{k+1}</M>, of the
element <C>[[i,g]]</C>  in <M>M_k</M>. The value of this might be <K>fail</K>. 
However, currently (version 1.8.4) some Hap functions assume that
<C>homotopy</C> is a function without testing.</Item>

<Item><C>properties</C>, a list of pairs <C>["name","value"]</C> "name" is a
string and value is anything (boolean, number, string...). Every
<C>HapResolution</C> (regardless of representation) has to have
<C>["type","resolution"]</C>, <C>["length",length]</C> where <C>length</C> is
the length of the resolution and <C>["characteristic",char]</C>. Currently (Hap
1.8.6), <C>length</C> must not be <K>infinity</K>.
The values of these properties can be tested using the Hap function
<C>EvaluateProperty(resolution,propertyname)</C>.</Item>

</List>

Note that making <C>HapResolution</C>s immutable will make the <C>.elts</C>
component immutable. As this lookup table might change during calculations,
we do not recommend using immutable resolutions (in any representation).
</Section>

<Section Label="largegrouprep"><Heading>The <K>HapLargeGroupResolutionRep</K> Representation</Heading>

In this sub-representation of the standard representation, the module elements
in this resolution are lists of groupring elements.
So the lookup table <C>.elts</C> is not used as long as no conversion to
standard representation takes place.
In addition to the components of a <K>HapResolution</K>, a resolution in large
group representation has the following components:

<List>
<Item><C>boundary2(resolution,term,gen)</C>, a function that returns the
boundary of the <A>gen</A>th generator of the <A>term</A>th module.</Item>
<Item><C>groupring</C> the group ring of the resolution <A>resolution</A>.</Item>
<Item><C>dimension2(resolution,term)</C> a function that returns the dimension
of the <A>term</A>th module of the resolution <A>resolution</A>.</Item>
</List>
The effort of having two versions of <C>boundary</C> and <C>dimension</C> is
necessary to keep the structure compatible with the usual Hap resolution.
</Section>

</Chapter>



<!-- ================================================== -->


<Chapter><Heading>Accessing and Manipulating Resolutions</Heading>


<Section><Heading>Representation-Independent Access Methods</Heading>

All methods listed below take a <C>HapResolution</C> in any representation. If
the other arguments are compatible with the representation of the resolution,
the returned value will be in the form defined by this representation. If the
other arguments are in a different representation, &GAP;s method selection is
used via <C>TryNextMethod()</C> to find an applicable method (a suitable representation).
<P/>

The idea behind this is that the results of computations have the same form as
the input. And as all representations are sub-representations of the
<C>HapResolutionRep</C> representation, input which is compatible with the
<C>HapResolutionRep</C> representation is always valid.
<P/>

Every new representation must support the functions of this section.

<ManSection>
 <Meth Name="StrongestValidRepresentationForLetter" Arg="resolution term
letter"/>
 <Returns>filter</Returns>
 <Description>
  Finds the sub-representation of <C>HapResolutionRep</C> for which
  <A>letter</A> is a valid letter of the <A>term</A>th module of
  <A>resolution</A>. Note that <A>resolution</A> automatically is in some
  sub-representation of <C>HapResolutionRep</C>.This is mainly meant for
  debugging.
 </Description>
</ManSection>


<ManSection>
 <Meth Name="StrongestValidRepresentationForWord" Arg="resolution term
word"/>
 <Returns>filter</Returns>
 <Description>
  Finds the sub-representation of <C>HapResolutionRep</C> for which
  <A>word</A> is a valid word of the <A>term</A>th module of
  <A>resolution</A>. Note that <A>resolution</A> automatically is in some
  sub-representation of <C>HapResolutionRep</C>. This is mainly meant for
  debugging. 
 </Description>
</ManSection>


<ManSection>
 <Meth Name="PositionInGroupOfResolution" Arg="resolution g" />
 <Meth Name="PositionInGroupOfResolutionNC" Arg="resolution g"/>
 <Returns>positive integer</Returns>
  <Description>
   This returns the position of the group element <A>g</A> in the enumeration
   of the group of <A>resolution</A>. The NC version does not check if <A>g</A>
   really is an element of the group of <A>resolution</A>.
  </Description>
</ManSection>


<ManSection>
 <Meth Name="IsValidGroupInt" Arg="resolution n"/>
 <Returns>boolean</Returns>
  <Description>
   Returns true if the <A>n</A>th element of the group of <A>resolution</A> is known.
  </Description>
</ManSection>

<ManSection>
 <Meth Name="GroupElementFromPosition" Arg="resolution n"/>
 <Returns>group element or <K>fail</K></Returns>
  <Description>
   Returns <A>n</A>th element of the group of <A>resolution</A>. If the
   <A>n</A>th element is not known, <K>fail</K> is returned.
  </Description>
</ManSection>


<ManSection>
 <Meth Name="MultiplyGroupElts" Arg="resolution x y"/>
 <Returns>positive integer or group element, depending on the type of <A>x</A> and <A>y</A></Returns>
  <Description>
   If <C>x</C> and <C>y</C> are given in standard representation (i.e. as
   integers), this returns the position of the product of the group elements
   represented by the positive integers <A>x</A> and <A>x</A>.
   <P/>
   If <C>x</C> and <C>y</C> are given in any other representation, the returned
   group element will also be represented in this way.
  </Description>
</ManSection>


<ManSection>
 <Meth Name="MultiplyFreeZGLetterWithGroupElt" Arg="resolution letter g"/>
 <Returns>A letter</Returns>
  <Description>
   Multiplies the letter <A>letter</A> with the group element <A>g</A> and
   returns the result. If <A>resolution</A> is in standard representation,
   <A>g</A> has to be an integer and <A>letter</A> has to be a pair of
   integer. If <A>resolution</A> is in any other representation, <A>letter</A>
   and <A>g</A> can be in a form compatible with that representation or in the
   standard form (in the latter case, the returned value will also have
   standard form).
  </Description>
</ManSection>


<ManSection>
 <Meth Name="MultiplyFreeZGWordWithGroupElt" Arg="resolution word g"/>
 <Returns>A word</Returns>
  <Description>
   Multiplies the word <A>word</A> with the group element <A>g</A> and
   returns the result. If <A>resolution</A> is in standard representation,
   <A>g</A> has to be an integer and <A>word</A> has to be a list of pairs of
   integers. If <A>resolution</A> is in any other representation, <A>word</A>
   and <A>g</A> can be in a form compatible with that representation or in the
   standard form (in the latter case, the returned value will also have
   standard form).
  </Description>
</ManSection>


<ManSection>
 <Meth Name="BoundaryOfFreeZGLetter" Arg="resolution term letter"/>
 <Returns>free ZG word (in the same representation as <A>letter</A>)</Returns>
  <Description>
   Calculates the boundary of the letter (word of length 1) <A>letter</A> of
   the <A>term</A>th module of <A>resolution</A>.
   <P/>
   The returned value is a word of the <A>term</A>-1st module and comes in the
   same representation as <A>letter</A>.
  </Description>
</ManSection>


<ManSection>
 <Meth Name="BoundaryOfFreeZGWord" Arg="resolution term word"/>
 <Returns>free ZG word (in the same representation as <A>letter</A>)</Returns>
  <Description>
   Calculates the boundary of the word <A>word</A> of
   the <A>term</A>th module of <A>resolution</A>.
   <P/>
   The returned value is a word of the <A>term</A>-1st module and comes in the
   same representation as <A>word</A>.
  </Description>
</ManSection>


</Section>


<Section><Heading>Converting Between Representations</Heading>

Four methods are provided to convert letters and words from standard
representation to any other representation and back again.

<ManSection>
 <Meth Name="ConvertStandardLetter" Arg="resolution term letter"/>
 <Meth Name="ConvertStandardLetterNC" Arg="resolution term letter"/>
 <Returns>letter in the representation of <A>resolution</A></Returns>
  <Description>
   Converts the letter <A>letter</A> in standard representation to the
   representation of <A>resolution</A>. The NC version does not check whether
   <A>letter</A> really is a letter in standard representation.
  </Description>
</ManSection>


<ManSection>
 <Meth Name="ConvertStandardWord" Arg="resolution term word"/>
 <Meth Name="ConvertStandardWordNC" Arg="resolution term word"/>
 <Returns>word in the representation of <A>resolution</A></Returns>
  <Description>
   Converts the word <A>word</A> in standard representation to the
   representation of <A>resolution</A>. The NC version does not check whether
   <A>word</A> is a valid word in standard representation.
  </Description>
</ManSection>


<ManSection>
 <Meth Name="ConvertLetterToStandardRep" Arg="resolution term letter"/>
 <Meth Name="ConvertLetterToStandardRepNC" Arg="resolution term letter"/>
 <Returns>letter in standard representation</Returns>
  <Description>
   Converts the letter <A>letter</A> in the representation of <A>resolution</A>
   to the standard representation. The NC version does not check whether
   <A>letter</A> is a valid letter of <A>resolution</A>.
  </Description>
</ManSection>

<ManSection>
 <Meth Name="ConvertWordToStandardRep" Arg="resolution term word"/>
 <Meth Name="ConvertWordToStandardRepNC" Arg="resolution term word"/>
 <Returns>word in standard representation</Returns>
  <Description>
   Converts the word <A>word</A> in the representation of <A>resolution</A>
   to the standard representation. The NC version does not check whether
   <A>word</A> is a valid word of <A>resolution</A>.
  </Description>
</ManSection>


</Section>


<Section><Heading>Special Methods for <K>HapResolutionRep</K></Heading>

Some methods explicitely require the input to be in the standard
representation (<A>HapResolutionRep</A>). Two of these test if a word/letter is
really in standard representation, the other ones are non-check versions of the
universal methods.

<ManSection>
 <Meth Name="IsFreeZGLetter" Arg="resolution term letter"/>
 <Returns>boolean</Returns>
  <Description>
   Checks if <A>letter</A> is an valid letter (word of length 1) in standard
   representation of the <A>term</A>th module of <A>resolution</A>.
  </Description>
</ManSection>


<ManSection>
 <Meth Name="IsFreeZGWord" Arg="resolution term word"/>
 <Returns>boolean</Returns>
  <Description>
   Check if <A>word</A> is a valid word in large standard representation of the
   <A>term</A>th module in <A>resolution</A>.
  </Description>
</ManSection>


<ManSection>
 <Meth Name="MultiplyGroupEltsNC" Arg="resolution x y"/>
 <Returns>positive integer</Returns>
  <Description>
   Given positive integers <C>x</C> and <C>y</C>, this returns the position of
   the product of the group elements  represented by the positive integers
   <A>x</A> and <A>x</A>. This assumes that all input is in standard
   representation and does not check the input.
  </Description>
</ManSection>


<ManSection>
 <Meth Name="MultiplyFreeZGLetterWithGroupEltNC" Arg="resolution letter g"/>
 <Returns>A letter in standard representation</Returns>
  <Description>
   Multiplies the letter <A>letter</A> with the group element represented by 
   the positive integer <A>g</A> and
   returns the result. The input is assumed to be in <A>HapResolutionRep</A>
   and is not checked.
  </Description>
</ManSection>


<ManSection>
 <Meth Name="MultiplyFreeZGWordWithGroupEltNC" Arg="resolution word g"/>
 <Returns>A letter in standard representation</Returns>
  <Description>
   Multiplies the word <A>word</A> with the group element represented by 
   the positive integer <A>g</A> and
   returns the result. The input is assumed to be in <A>HapResolutionRep</A>
   and is not checked.
  </Description>
</ManSection>


<ManSection>
 <Meth Name="BoundaryOfFreeZGLetterNC" Arg="resolution term letter"/>
 <Returns>free ZG word in standard representation</Returns>
  <Description>
   Calculates the boundary of the letter (word of length 1) <A>letter</A> of
   the <A>term</A>th module of <A>resolution</A>.
   The input is assumed to be in standard representation and not checked.
  </Description>
</ManSection>



<ManSection>
 <Meth Name="BoundaryOfFreeZGWordNC" Arg="resolution term word"/>
 <Returns>free ZG word in standard representation</Returns>
  <Description>
   Calculates the boundary of the word <A>word</A> of
   the <A>term</A>th module of <A>resolution</A>.
   The input is assumed to be in standard representation and not checked.
  </Description>
</ManSection>


</Section>

<#Include SYSTEM "./resolutionAccess_GroupRing.xml">

</Chapter>

<Chapter><Heading>Contracting Homotopies</Heading>

<#Include SYSTEM "./contraction.xml">
</Chapter>

</Body>
</Book>